let's start with lecture 11 which is about
input output systems or I/O systems that you have
the reading instructions for that main
book of the course and the extra facultative
reading as always and this is the agenda for
today we're going to start of course with
the introduction
at this point in the course we know that the
main job of your computer is basically to
process stuff crunch data and perform I/O
and this usually depends on what the user
is doing / on requests from the user
we have the hardware and we have the operating
system that is there to help managing and controlling
I/O operations and also coordinate the devices
that we have for I/O so what we will do in this
lecture is discuss and explore a bit the structure
of the part of the operating system that is
about I/O
we will see why there are as always tradeoffs
and complexities also when it comes to that
part of the operating system and discuss a
bit performance we will see why choices we
have / choices we make the operating system
level and at the hardware level have an impact
on performance is not really something new
because now if you
understand how virtual memory works for example
you know that it is fast also because we
have interrupts and that is one of the many
examples of cooperation between the operating
system and the hardware that i keep mentioning
since the beginning of the course
so the first the main challenge from the perspective
of I/O is to control in a good
way all the devices that you have connected
to the architecture so to your computer for example
so why is it challenging? you have completely
different types of devices
some of them are defined to give only
input or only output some of them are bidirectional
so you can either write or read from
them and when the devices fail the consequences
of a possible failure can go from almost unnoticeable
to
disaster some of them require control
in real time because it works only if you
operate on them within strict deadlines
for others deadlines
are not really that important so if the computer
is late reading a key you're pressing in your keyboard
by a couple of milliseconds you don't
even notice if the
operating system that controls the flaps of
a plane is late in fixing them or changing the
position you might as well notice that very
well so one thing is variability but it is
also challenging because opposite or in
contrast to variability you want standardization
if you have more and more type of devices
on the other hand you would like to have less
and less types or general types of devices
when it comes to the operating system point
of view you cannot really treat each different
mouse each different keyboard as a separate
thing
you want to have the concept of a keyboard
the concept of a mouse we want to keep it
simple in order for the operating system also
to be simple and modular and so on and this is
what I mention before each device has its own
oddities think of the wing flaps
example so to take care of I/O this is
what we said before the operating system has
part of it a submodule that is in the kernel
and it's about input output but it also relies
on so-called drivers so on external components
that basically allow to do this translation
from
a generic keyboard to a specific keyboard
that you are using or a generic disk to a
specific disk you're using and so on and so forth
at this point i hope that it becomes clearer
why a specific brand of computers that only
produces three types of computers and updates
them only once a year and delivers both the
hardware
as well as the operating system has a easier
job in claiming that their operating system
is stable than another company that only does
the operating system and wants that operating
system to basically work on any laptop that
is out there any type of hardware and so on
and so forth hopefully now you should get a better
understanding of
what is happening behind